<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A briefe cronicle and perfect rehearsall of all the memorable actions hapned not onelie in the Low Countries, but also in Germanie, Italy, Fraunce, Spaine, England, Turkie, and other countries since the yeare of our Lord 1500 to this present yeare 1598.]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855187</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855187</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20663</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08067)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20663)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 713:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A briefe cronicle and perfect rehearsall of all the memorable actions hapned not onelie in the Low Countries, but also in Germanie, Italy, Fraunce, Spaine, England, Turkie, and other countries since the yeare of our Lord 1500 to this present yeare 1598.]</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[J. Windet for] J. Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect as filmed; title page too dark, affecting readability of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE <hi>CRONICLE, and perfect rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall</hi> of all the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable actions hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not onelie in the low-Countries, but alſo in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, Ita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, Fraunce, Spaine, England, Turkie, and other</hi> Countries ſince the yeare of our Lord. 1500. to this preſent yeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ohn Wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE CHRONICLE AND perfect rehearſall of all the memorable actions happened not only in the Low-Countries, but alſo in Germanie, Italie, Fraunce, Spaine, England, Turkey, and other Countries, ſince the yeare of our Lord 1500. to this preſent yeare 1598.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1500</label> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this yeare vppon the <hi>25.</hi> day of the moneth of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie, the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift was borne in the towne of <hi>Gaunt</hi> in Flaunders, and in the ſame yere about the beginning of Sommer in <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Luke-land,</hi> there ſell Croſſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers colours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:3"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1502</label> This yeare there was ſo great a death in <hi>Germany,</hi> that the common ſpeech among them was, that all thoſe on whom the bloody Croſſes fell the yeare before ſhould die, &amp; at the ſame time there fell ſuch a Haile by <hi>Vitupord</hi> in <hi>Brabrant,</hi> as the like was neuer ſeene, for the haile ſtones were as big as any Tennis ball.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1503</label> This yeare about the laſt of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in the afternoone, all the Towne of <hi>Herderwicke</hi> was burnt in the ſpace of three houres, ſo that there remained but three or foure houſes, by the which fire there were ſmothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red aboue <hi>1500</hi> men, and al that was within the houſes kurnt.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare there were <hi>200.</hi> houſes burnt in <hi>Gorcum,</hi> and at <hi>Belle</hi> in <hi>Flaunders 500</hi> houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1504</label> This yeare died <hi>Iſabell</hi> Queene of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1506</label> About the beginning of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:20663:3"/>preparation, was made to bring king <hi>Phillip</hi> and his wife into <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare when king <hi>Phillip</hi> was gone into <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Gelders began againe to war vppon <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Brabrant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare about the <hi>27.</hi> of September, died <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Granado</hi> preſently after his Coronation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1507</label> The Towne of <hi>Tienen</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by thoſe of Gelder, with the aide of certaine Frenchmen, which was done vpon Saint <hi>Michaels</hi> day, and <hi>Turnholt</hi> ſpoyled.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1508</label> The <hi>8.</hi> of September there arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued two ſhips at <hi>Teruere</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> that came fro the <hi>Canaries,</hi> being the firſt ſhips that euer ſailed out of <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> or the Iſlands, they were laden with <hi>Canarie</hi> Sugars, the ſhips went to <hi>Antwarpe,</hi> &amp; there offered the Suger to be ſold for two
<pb facs="tcp:20663:4"/>blankes a pound, but they could not ſell it for ſo much.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Prince <hi>Charles</hi> with the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> his Grandfather, made his entrye into <hi>Gaunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1509</label> On the xiiij. of October, there was an Earthquake in the Cittie of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> that continued for the ſpace of <hi>18</hi> dayes, ſo that the walles of the Citie, and all the houſes vpon the Sea ſide fell downe, and the ſea roſe ſo high that it flowed ouer the walles of the Towne, and drowned aboue <hi>14000.</hi> men.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1510</label> There happened wars betweene <hi>Hans</hi> King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and the Townes of <hi>Holland, zealand,</hi> &amp; <hi>Freze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> againſt certaine Townes lying vppon the ſea: as, <hi>Lubecke, Roſtocke,</hi> and their adherents, which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſpace of two yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1511</label> The Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> held
<pb facs="tcp:20663:4"/>a Parliament of the ſtates of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> at <hi>Ausberg,</hi> where there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought before him, that was ſo great that he eate a whole Calfe and a Sheepe raw at one meale, and yet was not ſuffized.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1512</label> There was ſuch a Froſt for the ſpace of nine weekes, that in many places men went on foote vpon the ſalt water.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1513</label> This yeare <hi>Henry</hi> the right King of England, landed at <hi>Callis</hi> with a great power of men, &amp; from thence entered into the frontiers of <hi>Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> to make warre againſt the king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and at that time hee tooke <hi>Turwin</hi> &amp; <hi>Turney</hi> and built a Caſtle in <hi>Turney.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1514</label> In the moneth of Ianuarie at <hi>Wittenberge</hi> in <hi>Saxonie</hi> there was three Sunnes ſeene in the aire, and in each Sunne a bloody ſworde, the eleauenth of the ſame moneth, ware
<pb facs="tcp:20663:5"/>three Moones likewiſe ſeene.</p>
            <p>The <hi>7.</hi> of March, there were two raine bowes ſeene in the aire that ſtood backe to backe.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare in <hi>Layden</hi> there was a Child borne without a heade, with eyes &amp; mouth in the breſt, the armes and handes ſticking cloſe by the ſides, and beneath it was round without legges or feet.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1515</label> The firſt of Ianuarie died <hi>Loys</hi> the eleueuth King of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vppon ſatterday after candlemas day, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> entred into <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and the next day after hee was inueſted Duke of <hi>Brabrant,</hi> &amp; receiued homage of al the <hi>17</hi> Prouinces.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1516</label> The <hi>20.</hi> of October the order of the Golden Fleece was holden by Prince <hi>Charles</hi> at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and <hi>Leenuerden</hi> was beſieged by the Guelders.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:5"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1517</label> The ſame yeare <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Auſtria</hi> went into <hi>Spaine,</hi> there to bee Crowned king.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Froſt was ſo great at <hi>Anwarpe</hi> that they went on foote ouer the Riuer of Scheld, &amp; people roade with Horſe, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons ouer the water into <hi>Brabrant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1518</label> Prince <hi>Charles</hi> was crowned King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> within the towne of <hi>Valedolet,</hi> and by <hi>Vento</hi> about <hi>1200.</hi> ſouldiers were ſlaine, that were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Blacke company, the ſame yeare likewiſe there was an accorde made betweene <hi>Brabrant</hi> &amp; <hi>Flanders,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſperen</hi> was won from the Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1519</label> The <hi>12</hi> of Ianuarie died <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the Emperour, Grandfather to <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> The ſame yere in the month of February <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis de Valois</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> bought the towne of <hi>Tourney,</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> king
<pb facs="tcp:20663:6"/>of <hi>England,</hi> for a great ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare wheate was ſold for <hi>12.</hi> ſtiuers, and Rie for <hi>9.</hi> ſtiuers the quarter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1520</label> This yeare vpon the <hi>23.</hi> of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Spaine</hi> was elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Emperour, and at <hi>Acen</hi> in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie</hi> hee receaued the Imperiall Crowne with great triumph.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare in the moneth of October there was three hundred houſes burnt in <hi>Romerſwald.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1521</label> The Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> laide the firſt ſtone of the foundation of the new quier of our Ladies church in <hi>Andwerpe,</hi> and ſpread the morter with a trowell.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vppon the <hi>19.</hi> of Nouember, there was <hi>70.</hi> pariſhes in <hi>Holland</hi> ouerflowne and drowned by force of the water that entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:20663:6"/>the land, and in the ſame moneth the Towne of <hi>Turney</hi> was beſieged by the Emperour, and vpon Saint <hi>Andrewes</hi> day it was taken, ſince which time it hath bin holden vnder the king of <hi>Spaines</hi> ſubiection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1522</label> The Iſland of <hi>Rodes</hi> was wonne by the Turke, and while it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, there roſe a muteny in <hi>And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe,</hi> the people ſaying that the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers were the cauſe of the dearth of corne, which as then was verye deare, the like did the women of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelen</hi> and <hi>Bruſſels</hi> againſt their Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare in the moneth of Aprill, by <hi>Egmont</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> there was a Fiſh taken, being of <hi>80.</hi> foote long, &amp; in greatnes correſpondent, whereof they made <hi>160.</hi> barrels of Fiſh beſides the in trailes.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon Palmeſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonday, at <hi>Konlen,</hi> there were <hi>2.</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:20663:7"/>borne that cloue faſt together, hauing two Heades, two Armes, and two feete, maiden Children, but dead borne. Vpon Saint <hi>Andrewes</hi> day the ſame yere a ſhippers wife o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Moerbeke</hi> baked a loafe of breade o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pure wheate, and when ſhe drewe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of the Ouen, it was as blacke as pitch.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1523</label> This yere in the month of March there was ſo great a ſtorme of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; lightning, that there fel haile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones as big as hennes egges, and of diuers colours.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare <hi>Rodes</hi> was againe wonne from the Turkes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1524</label> This yeare there was <hi>5.</hi> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand houſes burnt in the towne of <hi>Troy</hi> in <hi>Champania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1525</label> This yeare during the beſieging of <hi>Pauia,</hi> there roſe great trouble in <hi>Germanie</hi> for preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell by <hi>Martin Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:7"/>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> married the king of <hi>Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales</hi> Daughter in the Towne of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill</hi> in <hi>Spayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1526</label> This yeare vppon the <hi>25</hi> of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie happened the fearefull and cruel battaile before <hi>Pauia,</hi> betweene the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Francis</hi> king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> wherin the king of <hi>Fraunce</hi> was taken priſoner.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1527</label> This yeare vppon the ſeauenth of May <hi>Phillip</hi> eldeſt ſon to <hi>Charles,</hi> the Emperour was borne at <hi>Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolet</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the citie of Rome was beſieged and taken by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Charles,</hi> &amp; the Pope taken priſoner, and in ſcaling the walles the Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> was ſlaine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1528</label> This yere vpon the <hi>6.</hi> of March <hi>1500. Guelders</hi> and many Citizens of <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> robbed and ſpoyled the Towne of <hi>Hage</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:8"/>
            <p>This yeare the Ilande <hi>Peru</hi> was firſt found out.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vppon the firſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iune, the Biſhop of <hi>Vtrecht</hi> took<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the towne of <hi>Vtrecht</hi> from the <hi>Guel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders,</hi> ſlaying and impriſoning al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Captaines and ſouldiers, drow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning two Prebends, and beheadin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two Citizens.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1529</label> This yeare in the moneth of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie, the Frenchmen bearing, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imperiall armes by ſubtiltie, took<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the towne of <hi>Myllan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Turke beſie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged <hi>Vienna</hi> with an Armie of tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hundreth and fiftie thouſand men.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vppon Michael<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas day in the Euening, there die<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many people of the ſweating ſick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in <hi>Anwarpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1530</label> This yeare vppon the two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bruary the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Charles</hi> was crowned king of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bardie,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:8"/>within the towne of <hi>Bononia,</hi> where the Emperour kiſſed the Popes foote.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon the twentie foure of March, the firſt ſtone of the foundation of the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Machelen</hi> was laide, which before was holden in the Pallace.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vppon the fift of Nouember, foure hundred &amp; foure Pariſhes were drowned in the low-Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1531</label> This yeare the Emperour came to <hi>Collen,</hi> where <hi>Ferdinand</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was crowned king of <hi>Romains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare in the moneth of Auguſt, about Saint <hi>Laurence</hi> day, there was a Comet or Blazing ſtar ſeene in the Low-Countries.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare and moneth, there was a fiſh taken vpon the Sea ſide in <hi>Holland,</hi> of ſixtie eight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:9"/>being thirteene foote broad.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare there happened an Earthquake in <hi>Portingale,</hi> that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued for the ſpace of eight daies, wherby <hi>1050.</hi> houſes within <hi>Lisbon</hi> fell downe. This earthquake hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened ſometimes ſeauen or eight times a day, which made the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens for feare to leaue the towne, &amp; lie in the open fields.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1532</label> A woman in <hi>Germanie</hi> (beeing great with child) killed her huſband in the night time, and eate vp his left ſide with the arme, the reſt of the dead body ſhe boyled and kept it to eate.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare ouer the towne of <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Weſtfalie,</hi> there was a man all armed ſeene in the aire.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1533</label> This yeare <hi>Henry</hi> the eight king of England repudiated his wife <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin,</hi> daughter of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and married his ſecond wife
<pb facs="tcp:20663:9"/>called <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Bullen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Guelderland,</hi> with fiue thouſand men ouerthrew the power of the Earle of Eaſt <hi>Freeſland,</hi> beeing of fifteene thouſand men.</p>
            <p>The ſame yere vpon the ſixt of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober about twelue of the clocke at night, our Lady Church in <hi>Andwarp</hi> was burnt.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Towne of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> was increaſed and made greater, by Henry Earle of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe founded the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1534</label> This yeare vpon our Lady euen in the month of March, there aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled great numbers of men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, both of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Anabaptiſts, that ment to paſſe through <hi>Harlame</hi> to goe to <hi>Munſter</hi> but at blacke water they were taken and moſt of them burnt &amp; puniſhed.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalens</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:10"/>day, there was more then one thouſand houſes burnt in <hi>Breda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare <hi>Iohn van Layden,</hi> principall of the Anabaptiſts, with his company tooke the Towne of <hi>Munſter,</hi> driuing out the Biſhop and all the ſpiritualty: but beeing beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Emperours troupe, and conſtraind by hunger, it was wonne from him. <hi>Iohn Van Layden</hi> with his aſſociates were executed.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare, the towne <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaus</hi> in <hi>France</hi> was ſpoyled with thunder, and in three houres cleane burnt.</p>
            <p>The ſame yere the towne of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talbon</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> was in three houres ſpace cleane burnt &amp; conſumed with fire.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Anabaptiſts ranne naked through the towne of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and made great vprore.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1535</label> This yeare the Emperour with
<pb facs="tcp:20663:10"/>a great Armie ſayled into <hi>Africa:</hi> where he draue the Barbarians out of the towne of <hi>Tunis,</hi> and reſtored <hi>Muleaſſes</hi> to his kingdome againe.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare a Gentleman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aliue ſuncke into the earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee would not ſell corne to the poore people at a reaſonable price.</p>
            <p>This yeare Henry the eight King of <hi>England,</hi> in deſpight of the Pope (becauſe he would not conſent to the deuorce of Queene <hi>Katherin</hi>) permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1536</label> This yeare vppon the ninth of May the towne of <hi>Delft</hi> was burned and conſumed with fire in the ſpace of three houres. The ſame yere died <hi>Eraſmus</hi> of <hi>Roterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1537</label> This yere <hi>Francis</hi> king of <hi>France</hi> with fifty thouſand men tooke the towne of <hi>Hedding,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare and moneth the Earle of <hi>Buren</hi> burnt the townes of
<pb facs="tcp:20663:11"/>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Mutterell,</hi> &amp; beſieged <hi>Turwin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1538</label> This yeare <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſuppreſſed diuers Abbies and Cloyſters in England, keeping all their lands to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1539</label> This yeare vppon the ſecond of May <hi>Iſabell</hi> Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and Empreſſe and Daughter to the king of <hi>Portingale</hi> died at <hi>Toledo</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1541</label> This yeare the Emperour came out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and at <hi>Gaunt</hi> hee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed diuers rebels, and therein made a goodly Caſtle.</p>
            <p>The ſame yere the Summer was ſo hote, that the Riuer of <hi>Rhiin</hi> in ſome places was dried vp, ſo that men paſt ouer it on foote, the like did the Riuer of <hi>Seine</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and the Figges in <hi>Flanders</hi> were as ripe vppon the trees, as if they had come out of <hi>Spayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:11"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1542</label> This yeare vppon the twentie foure of Iune, warres were againe proclaimed betweene the Emperour and the King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare in the moneth of Iulie vpon Saint <hi>Iames</hi> day, <hi>Martin Van Roſſe,</hi> with great number of ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers came before <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and thought to haue ſurpreſſed the towne, hee burnt all the Milles in Saint <hi>Willebordes</hi> field, and from thence he went into <hi>Lukeland,</hi> where he was forced with ſhame to retire.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Emperours Souldiers tooke <hi>Deuentre</hi> and other townes from the Duke of <hi>Guelder</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare in <hi>Germanie</hi> after a raine, there fell great numbers of Graſhoppers, which did great hurt to the fruits of the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1543</label> This yeare the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> made <hi>Phillip</hi> his Son King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and married him with
<pb facs="tcp:20663:12"/>
               <hi>Mary</hi> the King of Portingales daughter.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Emperour came out of <hi>Spaine</hi> and went into <hi>Guelderland,</hi> where vpon the eight of Auguſt he beſieged <hi>Dueren,</hi> and willed them to yeelde it vnto him, but the townes men ſaid that they feared not a Haddocke eater: which not long after the Emperour made them dearely to rue, and at the ſame time <hi>Amerſford</hi> was taken by the <hi>Guelders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1544</label> This yeare the Scots through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Neatherland were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed enemies to the Emperour.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1545</label> This yere <hi>Charles,</hi> eldeſt Sonne to <hi>Phillip</hi> king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> was borne in <hi>Valedolet</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1546</label> This yere the Emperour made warre againſt the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> &amp; the Lantgraue of <hi>Heſſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Caſtle of
<pb facs="tcp:20663:12"/>Bla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kerhooke by <hi>Rammekens</hi> in <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheren</hi> was made.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon the eight of Auguſt, a lightning falling in the towne of <hi>Mechelen,</hi> blew vp a towre full of Gunpowder, and therwith ſlew at the leaſt <hi>1800.</hi> men, without any other hurt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1547</label> This yeare vppon the twentie foure of Aprill the Emperour tooke the Duke of <hi>Saxon</hi> priſoner, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrew his armie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1548</label> This yere the Emperour came into <hi>Brabant,</hi> bringing with him the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> and <hi>Phillip Lantgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſen</hi> priſoners.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1549</label> This yere <hi>Phillip</hi> king of <hi>Spaine</hi> came out of <hi>Spaine</hi> into the Low-Countries, where hee was inueſted with the gouerment thereof.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare about the thirteen of October, <hi>Phillip</hi> king of <hi>Spaine</hi> made his entry into <hi>Gaunt,</hi> and not
<pb facs="tcp:20663:13"/>long after into <hi>Anwarpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the next day after whitſonday, <hi>Katherine Demedices</hi> was Crowned Queene of <hi>France,</hi> within the towne of Saint <hi>Dennis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1550</label> This yeare the Chriſtians won <hi>Africa</hi> from the Turks and Moores, and then the paſſage from <hi>Bruſſels</hi> was begun to be digged.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon the twentie two of October, the Emperour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged <hi>Metz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This yeare the <hi>Lantgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> was diſcharged of his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1552</label> and ſet at libertie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1553</label> This yeare the Emperours Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie tooke the towne of <hi>Turwin</hi> which they ſpoyled, and raſed the walles to the ground.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Emperour tooke the towne of <hi>Hedding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1554</label> This yere <hi>Phillip</hi> king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> went into <hi>England</hi> to marrie <hi>Marie</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:13"/>Queene of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1555</label> This yeare died <hi>Iane</hi> Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> mother to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperor <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1556</label> This yeare king <hi>Phillip</hi> held his firſt feaſt of the order of the Golden Fleece in <hi>Andwarpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yere vpon the eighteene of Februarie died <hi>Martin Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare there was a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met ſeene, that continued for the ſpace of fourteene dayes, betokening (as ſome iudged) the warres which at that time began in the low coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare peace was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed betweene <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> king of <hi>France,</hi> and the ſame yere vpon the ſeauenteenth of September, the Emperour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of the Low Countries, to goe into <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1557</label> This yere vpon twelfe euen, the Frenchmen thought by treaſon to
<pb facs="tcp:20663:14"/>haue taken the towne of <hi>Doway,</hi> but they fayled of their purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine</hi> with an army of Neatherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, beſieged the towne of Saint <hi>Quintins,</hi> where the greateſt part of the nobilitie of <hi>France</hi> came to raiſe the ſiege: but they were almoſt all taken and ſlaine, &amp; vpon the twenty fiue of Auguſt after the towne was taken.</p>
            <p>The ſame yere was a great dearth: for at <hi>Andwarp</hi> Rie was ſold for viii, guilders, and wheat for xii. guilders the buſhell.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1558</label> This yeare <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> and <hi>Bohemia</hi> was elected Emperour.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Frenchmen made a road into <hi>Flaunders,</hi> where they robbed and burnt <hi>Dunkerke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yere vpon the fifteenth day of Iulie, <hi>Dunkerke</hi> was wonne
<pb facs="tcp:20663:14"/>againe from the Frenchmen, and all that were founde therein ſlaine and murthered.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon the twenty one of September, the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> died in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and vpon the eighteene of October, about <hi>28.</hi> dayes after the death of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour died <hi>Mary</hi> his Siſter.</p>
            <p>The ſame yere vpon the thirteene of December the Emperours Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall was celebrated within <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1559</label> This yeare vpon the third of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill, peace was determined at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braye</hi> between <hi>Phillip</hi> king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the French king, and king <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> married the eldeſt Daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and each of them redeliuered ſuch townes as they held by force.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare at the mariage of king <hi>Phillip</hi> with the French Kings daughter, <hi>Henry</hi> king of <hi>France</hi> run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:20663:15"/>at tilt, was by a ſplinter <hi>Monſieur Mongomries</hi> Launce thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> into the eye, wherof vpon the twe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of Iuly after he died.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon the twen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> nine of Iuly, King <hi>Phillip</hi> celebrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the order of the Golden Fleece the towne of <hi>Gaunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Dutcheſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Parma</hi> entred into the Neathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lands for regent thereof.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Scots bega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to profeſſe the Religion, and to lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Papiſtrie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1560</label> This yeare in the month of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuarie, king <hi>Phillip</hi> married <hi>Eliz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beth de Valois,</hi> daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſecond king of <hi>France</hi> in the tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Guarda la Iura</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vppon the twent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſixe of Februarie, the firſt ſtone of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> foundation of the new towne hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Andwarpe</hi> was laid.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:15"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1561</label> This yere was the firſt time that ſhippes ſayled in the newe Riuer of <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare diuers Biſhops were newly erected in certaine townes in the Neatherlands.</p>
            <p>The ſame yere the prince of <hi>Conde</hi> with diuers ſouldiers called Huge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, took certain townes in <hi>France:</hi> which hee did, by reaſon of certaine controuerſies that happened among the Nobilitie, touching the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an edict of peace, made in the behalfe of the religion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1562</label> This yeare the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> in the name of <hi>Charles</hi> king of <hi>France,</hi> tooke the Citie of <hi>Roane,</hi> and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diuers of the Citizens.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1563</label> This yeare in the month of May ouer the towne of <hi>Callis,</hi> there was ſeene in the aire, two men armed, &amp; all bloody to the knees, each of them bearing a ſhielde in his left hande,
<pb facs="tcp:20663:16"/>whereof the one had a Croſſe, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Lyon in it, and after them fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed two women apparelled in white.</p>
            <p>The ſame yere eight hundred hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were burnt within the towne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Poperin</hi> in <hi>Flaunders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare there was ſo grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a plague in <hi>England,</hi> that in <hi>Londo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> there died eighteene hundred men i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one weeke.</p>
            <p>This yere vpon the ſeuenteenth of May died <hi>Iohn Caluin.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1564,</label>
            </p>
            <p>This yeare the Riuer of <hi>Shelde</hi> froſe ſo hard, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1565</label> that the people ſolde wine and beere vppon the riuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Andwarpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This yeare vppon the fift of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1566</label> the Nobilitie and Gentlemen of the Low Countries preſented a petition to the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Parma,</hi> requeſting the moderation of all placarts publiſhed touching Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
<pb facs="tcp:20663:16"/>Vpon the fourth of Iuly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion began openly to bee preached in the Low Countries.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon the twentie of Auguſt Images in <hi>Andwarpe</hi> and other places were throwne downe.</p>
            <p>This yeare thoſe of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1567</label> ſtoode armed vppon the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brug, and the Papiſts at the bruge foot, one readie to ſet vpon the other, but by the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> means they were pacified.</p>
            <p>The one and twentie of Aprill the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hauing had intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence what was determined in <hi>Spaine</hi> touching the Low countries, and hauing aduertiſed the Earle of <hi>Egmont</hi> thereof, hee went into <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twenty two of Auguſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke <hi>D'Alua</hi> with great triumph (althogh vnworthie) was receiued into <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:17"/>
            <p>The ſame yeare vpon the ninth of September, the Earles of <hi>Fgmont</hi> &amp; <hi>Horne</hi> were committed to priſon by the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> and kept in the Caſtle of <hi>Gaunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeauenteenth of October, the Caſtle of <hi>Andwarpe</hi> was begun to be made.</p>
            <p>The laſt of December, the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of <hi>Parma</hi> departed out of the Low Countries, and preſently after the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> impriſoned diuers of the people that were of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuch as had borne armes.</p>
            <p>This yeare in Eaſter Holidaies the Earle <hi>Lodwicke</hi> tooke the houſe of <hi>Weden</hi> in <hi>Freeſeland</hi> and <hi>Dam,</hi> in the which enterpriſe, the Earle of <hi>Arenberch</hi> and diuers <hi>Spaniards</hi> were ouerthrowne.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Iulie the Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> cauſed the two Lordes of <hi>Baten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borch,</hi> and ſixteene gentlemen more
<pb facs="tcp:20663:17"/>to be beheaded.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Iuly the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> ſent his forces into <hi>Freeſland</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Earle <hi>Lodwicke</hi> that ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him, but becauſe the Dutch Souldiers would not fight, he was forced to ſaue himſelfe, and ſwam through the riuer of <hi>Embdze.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift of Iulie the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> cauſed the Earles of <hi>Egmont</hi> &amp; <hi>Horne</hi> to be beheaded in the towne of <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth of September, the Earle of <hi>Bueren</hi> was taken in <hi>Louen,</hi> &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied into <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the moneth of October the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> paſſed the Riuer of the <hi>Maſe</hi> at <hi>Stochem</hi> with certaine Dutch forces, but the Dutchmen when they ſhould fight, aſking for mony, were the cauſe that hee could not fight with the enemie, whervp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb facs="tcp:20663:18"/>he went into <hi>France,</hi> to ayde the <hi>Hugonots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This yeare vpon the thirteenth of march, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1569</label> the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> being taken priſoner, was trayterouſlie ſhot into the body by <hi>Monteſquion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This yeare vpon the ſixteenth of Iuly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1570</label> the Duk of <hi>Alua</hi> publiſhed a generall pardon within the towne of <hi>Andwarpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie fiue of September, <hi>Anna</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> took ſhipping in <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to ſayle into <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This moneth <hi>Ladron</hi> gouernour of <hi>Valencia,</hi> was by his Souldiers committed Priſoner, becauſe they would haue the pay of nyne compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſouldiers, the mony where of he had played at dice, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them to ſatiſfie, and to the ſame end he gotte diuers of them to <hi>And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe,</hi> where he committed and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
<pb facs="tcp:20663:18"/>at leaſt two &amp; forty of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall mutiners.</p>
            <p>This yere <hi>Harmon Ruyter</hi> tooke the Caſtle of <hi>Loeueſtein,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1571</label> which the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> not long after tooke from him againe, and hanged both him, &amp; all his companie.</p>
            <p>In the moneth of December, the mony that the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> ſhould haue receaued out of <hi>Spaine</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Queene of <hi>Englands</hi> ſhips and carrried into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This yeare in the moneth of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1572</label> the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> ſought to haue a tribute of the tenth penny, but he could not obtaine it.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Aprill, the <hi>Brill</hi> was taken by <hi>Lumine,</hi> and not long after <hi>Fluſhing</hi> and <hi>Enchuyſen</hi> yeelded to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> againſt the Duke of <hi>Alua.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:19"/>
            <p>The ninth of Aprill, <hi>Boſſu</hi> with certaine <hi>Spaniards,</hi> deſired to paſſe through <hi>Roterdam,</hi> where traiterou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly he murthered diuers Burgers, &amp; tooke in <hi>Delfeſhauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie foure of May, Earle <hi>Lodowicke</hi> tooke <hi>Bergen</hi> in <hi>Henegon,</hi> which the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, and tooke <hi>Bergen</hi> &amp; <hi>Valechyn</hi> againe.</p>
            <p>In Auguſt the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> with his armie beeing at <hi>Duesborge</hi> paſſed ouer the Rhein and tooke <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermonde,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lennen</hi> by compoſition, &amp; <hi>Mechelen</hi> yeelded of it ſelfe, that done, he went to <hi>Bergen Henegon</hi> to help the Earle <hi>Lodowick,</hi> but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great murther in <hi>France,</hi> hee could no helpe his Brother, and ſo paſſed through <hi>Mechelen</hi> into <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond of September, the
<pb facs="tcp:20663:19"/>Earle <hi>Lodowick</hi> by compoſition yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the towne of <hi>Bergen</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> vppon condition that hee ſhould bee conuaied ſafelie vnto the borders of <hi>Germanie,</hi> which was performed.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of October <hi>Mechelen</hi> was forcibly taken &amp; ſpoyled, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in many Burgers were murthred, &amp; women and maides deflowred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they receaued the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> into the towne.</p>
            <p>The twenty of October <hi>Monſieur Dragon</hi> paſſed his men through the water at <hi>Southberland</hi> towards <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thirteenth of Nouember, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> tooke <hi>Zutphen,</hi> where they vſed the Burgers very cruelly.</p>
            <p>The twentie of Nouember <hi>Don Fredericke</hi> entred into <hi>Narden,</hi> where contrary to his faith and promiſe he
<pb facs="tcp:20663:20"/>murthered diuers of the Burgers, &amp; burnt the towne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1573</label> This yeare <hi>Don Fredericke</hi> came before <hi>Harlem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie three of Aprill <hi>Sancy Dauila</hi> Captaine of the caſtle in <hi>And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe,</hi> with a great armie of ſhips, came before <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> where hee &amp; all his ſhippes were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the <hi>Fluſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thirteenth of Iulie, <hi>Harlem</hi> yeelded to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> committing themſelues to the Kinges mercy, which they did for want of victuals.</p>
            <p>The fourth of October the Caſtle of <hi>Ramekins</hi> in <hi>Zealand</hi> yeelded to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and not long after <hi>Gertrudenberg</hi> was taken by <hi>Poyet,</hi> Liefetenant to the Prince.</p>
            <p>The eight of October, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> beſieged <hi>Alcmar,</hi> but by reaſon of the water they were forced to leaue it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:20"/>
            <p>The twelfth of October, the Earle of <hi>Boſſu</hi> with a great Nauy of ſhips came before <hi>Enchehuſen:</hi> where hee was taken, &amp; ſent priſoner to <hi>Horne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In December the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> went into <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1574</label> This yeare the King of <hi>Spayne</hi> ſent <hi>Don Loys de requeſentie</hi> (Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of Saint <hi>Iacobs</hi> order, and of the houſe of the Dukes of <hi>Coſa</hi>) into the Low Countries to bee Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, he thought to haue rayſed the Princes ſiege before <hi>Midleborow,</hi> but the twenty foure of Ianuarie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were ouerthrown at <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen.</hi> The ſixt of Februarie <hi>Monſieur Dragon</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Midleburge</hi> yeelded vp the towne to the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift of Aprill, the Commaunder publiſhed a generall pardon within the towne of <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:21"/>
            <p>The twentie foure of Aprill, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ouerthrew the Princes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie at <hi>Mokerheye,</hi> their Generall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Duke <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> ſon to the <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſgraue</hi> of <hi>Rhein,</hi> Earle <hi>Lodowicke,</hi> and Earle <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Naſſawe,</hi> who were neuer found eyther dead or a liue.</p>
            <p>The twenty ſixe of Aprill, the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> in <hi>Andwarpe</hi> cried, <hi>fuere, fuere, Viliacoes,</hi> becauſe they would bee paid.</p>
            <p>The xxvj. of May, the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> came again before <hi>Leyden,</hi> and beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, where before it they made <hi>22.</hi> Bulwarkes.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time the Princes ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with certaine ſhips came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and there tooke cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſhips in the ſight of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander.</p>
            <p>The third of October, the towne of <hi>Leyden</hi> was miraculouſly relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb facs="tcp:20663:21"/>and the ſiege rayſed by meanes of Captaine <hi>Boyſet</hi> with a Fleete of ſhips, that entered into it bywater.</p>
            <p>In December, an aſſemblye was holden at <hi>Breda,</hi> betweene the Commaunder and the Prince and States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> to make a peace.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1575</label> This yeare the towne and caſtle of <hi>Bueren</hi> was by the Gouernour thereof deliuered vnto the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare <hi>Bomell</hi> was beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the whole ſummer long.</p>
            <p>The twelfth of Iulie, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> maried <hi>Charlote</hi> daughter to <hi>Monſieur de Monpenſier</hi> within the towne of <hi>Brill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twelfth of Auguſt <hi>Shooneho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> was by compoſition yeelded to the enemie.</p>
            <p>The twentie eight of Auguſt <hi>Old-water</hi> was forcibly taken by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:22"/>&amp; many of the Burgers mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</p>
            <p>The eight of September, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> beſieged <hi>Wert,</hi> &amp; not long after it yeelded vp.</p>
            <p>The twenty eight of September the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> paſſed the waters at Saint <hi>Anneſlant, Duyuelant,</hi> and <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſlant,</hi> where <hi>Boyſet</hi> was ſlaine, there they tooke the fort of <hi>Bonnuene</hi> and beſieged <hi>Zuriczee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1576</label> This yeare the twentie of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie, the Princes ſouldiers tooke <hi>Krimpen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift of march the Commander died in <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In May the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> tooke <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riczee,</hi> and not long after they left <hi>Zealand,</hi> and went to <hi>Aelſt,</hi> and tooke the towne.</p>
            <p>The twentie three of September, <hi>Monſieur de Heſſe</hi> Gouernor of <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:22"/>and the Lorde-<hi>Glunes</hi> with the aide of the Burgers, tooke the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalleſt of the ſtates, being in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell within <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie of October the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes</hi> tooke <hi>Maſtricke,</hi> by meanes of the Dutch Souldiers that lay in it, wherin they robbed, ſpoyled, &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered without mercy.</p>
            <p>The ſame day <hi>Don Iohn de Auſtria,</hi> came to <hi>Lutzenburgh,</hi> and was ſent by the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> to bee Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Low Countries.</p>
            <p>The fourth of Nouember, was the furie of <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> which was done by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that iſſued out of the Caſtle into the towne, wherin they ſlew about <hi>9500.</hi> men Burgers, and Souldiers, <hi>4000.</hi> drowned with the Earle of <hi>Ouerſteine,</hi> burnt ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred houſes, and ranſomed the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:23"/>
            <p>The eight of Nouember, peace was made at <hi>Gaunt</hi> betwene the Prince, &amp; the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift of Nouember, the towne of <hi>Valencia,</hi> cauſed the Dutch Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to depart out of the towne, and by appointment the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vp the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>The ninth of Nouember the Earle of <hi>Krulx</hi> Gouernor of <hi>Flanders,</hi> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Caſtle of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> yeelded by compoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1577</label> This yeare vppon the eighteene of Februarie, thoſe of <hi>Vtrecht</hi> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Caſtle, and compelled the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to yeeld it to <hi>Boſſu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie ſeauen of February, the peace agreed vppon with <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> was proclaimed in <hi>Andwarpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie of March the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> went out of the Caſtle of <hi>And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:23"/>&amp; the Prince of <hi>Chima</hi> kept it.</p>
            <p>Vppon May day, <hi>Don Iohn</hi> was with great honor receaued into <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eleauenth of Iuly, <hi>Don Iohn</hi> went to <hi>Mechelen,</hi> where hee ſent for the Dutch Captaines of that towne, and of the towne and Caſtle of <hi>And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe,</hi> and commanded them to keep the townes for him. He ſent likewiſe for the Prince of <hi>Chima,</hi> and in his place ſent <hi>Monſieur Tourlon,</hi> &amp; from thence he went to <hi>Namen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond of Iuly, betweene <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimghen,</hi> and <hi>Hefimghen,</hi> there was a Fiſh taken of fiftie right foot long, &amp; fortie foote thicke.</p>
            <p>The twenty nine of Iuly, <hi>Don Iohn</hi> took the Caſtle of <hi>Namen,</hi> which was the cauſe of a new warre.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Auguſt, <hi>Tourlon</hi> was taken in the Caſtle of <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:20663:24"/>his Souldiers driuen out, who with the high Dutchmen tooke the new towne, and there inſconſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>The twentie eight of Auguſt, <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Bours</hi> diliuered the caſtle vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Burgers that broke it downe on the ſide that ioineth to the towne.</p>
            <p>The twenty eight of September. the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> entred into <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and the <hi>22.</hi> he road to <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> and the <hi>24.</hi> hee was choſen Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour.</p>
            <p>The eighteene of October, thoſe of <hi>Gaunt</hi> tooke the Duke of <hi>Aerſchot</hi> priſoner, to get their priueledges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>The ſame time alſo they tooke the Biſhops of <hi>Ipre,</hi> and of <hi>Brugges,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Raſſingen Campany,</hi> and the chiefe Baylie of <hi>Ipre</hi> and <hi>Cortricke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie one of Nouember,
<pb facs="tcp:20663:24"/>Duke <hi>Mathias</hi> entred into the Low-Countries to be their Gouernour.</p>
            <p>The ſeauenth of December <hi>Don Iohn</hi> with his ſouldiers, were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed enemies to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1578</label> This yeare vpon the eighteene of Ianuarie, Duke <hi>Mathias</hi> was ſworne Gouernor within the town of <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt of Ianuarie, the riters of <hi>Don Iohn de Auſtria</hi> ouerthrewe the States troupes hard by <hi>Namen,</hi> and tooke <hi>Giblon, Leuuen, Aerſchot, Tenen, Dieſt,</hi> and <hi>Sichem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eight of Februarie, <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> agreed with the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie two of Aprill, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification of <hi>Gaunt</hi> was publiſhed &amp; ſworne in <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and the Ieſuits refuſing to doe it, were by ſhip ſent out of the towne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:25"/>
            <p>The twentie of Iulie the Dutch ſouldiers that lay in Campe, yeelded vp the towne that was beſieged by the Earle of <hi>Rennenburg,</hi> that held it for the States.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Auguſt, the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> ſet vppon the States Souldiers by <hi>Rymenant, Boſſu</hi> beeing their beadle: where <hi>Don Iohn</hi> loſt many of his men.</p>
            <p>The twenty foure of September, certain <hi>Wallons</hi> mutined vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their pay, and by the help of <hi>Montigny</hi> made warre vppon <hi>Gaunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare the Goſpell was openly preached throughout <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Flaunders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of October, <hi>Don Iohn de Auſtria,</hi> died of the plague, and in his place entred the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ninteenth of Nouember, the Earle of <hi>Renuenburg</hi> had the towne
<pb facs="tcp:20663:25"/>
               <hi>Deuenter</hi> deliuered vnto him by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1579</label> This yeare in the month of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> took the Caſtle of <hi>Weert,</hi> and then came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Maſtricht.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the ſame time the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſories of the States met at <hi>Kenlen,</hi> to intreat of peace.</p>
            <p>The twenty nine of Iuly, the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes</hi> tooke <hi>Maſtricht</hi> by aſſault, and entred it by force.</p>
            <p>The twenty of October Captaine <hi>La Noue</hi> tooke <hi>Meen</hi> againe, with the Caſtles of <hi>Halewin</hi> and <hi>Waerwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1580</label> This yere vpon the twenty ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of Februarie, the Earle of <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> took <hi>Cortright</hi> for the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Aprill <hi>Mechelen</hi> was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for the States, by <hi>Monſieur Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeuenteene of Iuly, the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:26"/>tooke <hi>Delfe</hi> Ile, and <hi>Cowerden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1581</label> Vpon the fourteene of Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in the towne of <hi>Steenwicke,</hi> was releeued by the Lord of <hi>Nieuenort,</hi> &amp; Coronell <hi>Norris,</hi> where many <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> were ſlaine.</p>
            <p>The twenty three of Iune, <hi>Breda</hi> by meanes of <hi>Freſin</hi> that lay priſoner in the Caſtle was betraied and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The xviii. of Auguſt, the towne of <hi>Cambray</hi> was deliuered by the Duke of <hi>Alenſon,</hi> which the Prince of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> had beſieged.</p>
            <p>The ſeauenth of September <hi>End<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houen</hi> was taken, and not long after taken againe from the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth of October, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> tooke <hi>Dornicke</hi> by compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after hee had many times aſſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it.</p>
            <p>The twentie nine of October,
<pb facs="tcp:20663:26"/>Duke <hi>Mathias</hi> went out of the Low-Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1582</label> This yeare vpon the ninteene of Februarie, the Duke <hi>Alenſon</hi> by ſhip at riued in <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and the twenty two of the ſame moneth, hee was ſworne Gouernour of the Countrie of the States.</p>
            <p>The eighteene of March the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was ſhotte into the heade within the towne of <hi>Andwarpe</hi> by one <hi>Iohn Iauregni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ninteene of Aprill the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> beſieged <hi>Andenard,</hi> &amp; tooke it for want of aide.</p>
            <p>The twentie three of Aprill <hi>Monſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our de Tion, Tempel,</hi> and <hi>Monſieour de la Guard</hi> tooke <hi>Aelſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eleauenth of Iulie, <hi>Nicholas Zalcedo</hi> thought to haue ſlaine the Duke of <hi>Alenſon,</hi> but hee was taken and brought to <hi>Paris,</hi> where vppon
<pb facs="tcp:20663:27"/>the twentie two of October, he was torne in peeces by foure horſes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Auguſt, the Scots that lay in <hi>Liere</hi> betraied the towne, and deliuered it to the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fifteene of Auguſt the Duke <hi>Alenſon</hi> was receiued into the town of <hi>Gaunt</hi> as Earle of <hi>Flaunders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The xxiii. of September, <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem</hi> was deliuered by the Earle of <hi>Hollocke,</hi> wherin were three Earles.</p>
            <p>The ſame moneth the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> tooke <hi>Nieuenhouen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1583</label> This yeare the ſeuenteene of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie, the French furie happened in <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> where the Duke <hi>Alenſon</hi> vnder pretence of a muſter meant to haue betraied it, in the which enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe he loſt fifteene hundred French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, beſides hurt men &amp; priſoners, and but <hi>83.</hi> Burgers ſlaine,</p>
            <p>The thirteenth of Februarie, the
<pb facs="tcp:20663:27"/>new Burſe of <hi>Andwarpe</hi> was burnt.</p>
            <p>In Auguſt the Spaniards tooke <hi>Dixmuyden,</hi> and in December they beſieged <hi>Ipre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twenty foure of October, the Spaniards tooke <hi>Sas</hi> by <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thirteenth of October, the baylie of <hi>Waſt</hi> deliuered the land of <hi>Waſt</hi> to the Spaniards, and they of <hi>Andwarpe</hi> cut the Diches.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1584</label> In this yere in the month of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie, <hi>Aelſt</hi> was deliuered to the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twelfth of April the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> tooke <hi>Ipre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth of Inne, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> beſieged the ſconce of <hi>Lillo,</hi> but hee was forced to leaue it with ſhame.</p>
            <p>The tenth of Iuly, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> tooke <hi>Liefekins hooke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame day the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:28"/>was ſlaine in <hi>Delf</hi> by one <hi>Balthazer Gerrats,</hi> the ſame month the States loſt <hi>Herentales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixteene of Auguſt, <hi>Dermond</hi> was deliuered to the Prince of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentic ſix of September, the towne of <hi>Gaunt</hi> for want of victnals yeelded to the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1585,</label> This yeare Graue <hi>Holocke</hi> tooke <hi>Hertogenboſh,</hi> but hec was forced to leane it againe with ſome loſſe of his men.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vppon Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> euening, the bridge by <hi>Calco</hi> was fully finiſhed.</p>
            <p>The tenth of March, <hi>Bruſſels</hi> for want of victuals agreed with the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth of Aprill the ſhips that were ſet on fire, and ſent by them of <hi>Andwarpe</hi> to fire the bridge, entred
<pb facs="tcp:20663:28"/>vnder it and did much hurt.</p>
            <p>The ſame time the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and <hi>Zealanders</hi> took in <hi>Liefskins hooke,</hi> S. <hi>Annes hooke,</hi> and <hi>Venten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeauenteene of Iuly, the towne of <hi>Mechelen</hi> for want of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals yeelded to the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth of Auguſt an agreement was made betweene <hi>England</hi> and the Low Countries.</p>
            <p>The eleuenth of Auguſt the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> receaued the Golden Fleece at the bridge of <hi>Calloo</hi> on <hi>Brabant</hi> ſide.</p>
            <p>The twenty ſeauen of Auguſt the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> entred into <hi>And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond of September the bridge was broken.</p>
            <p>The ninth of Nouember, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Caſtle of <hi>Andwarpe</hi> were digged againe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:29"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1586</label> This yeare about the beginning thereof the Earle of <hi>Leceſter</hi> came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Holland,</hi> and the ſixt of Februarie after was proclaimed Gouernour.</p>
            <p>The ſixt of Iune the towne of <hi>Graue</hi> by compoſition yeelded to the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twenty nine of Iune he tooke <hi>Venlo</hi> likewiſe by compoſition.</p>
            <p>The ſixteene of Iuly the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tooke <hi>Axel</hi> in <hi>Flaunders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeuenteene of Iuly the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> beſieged the towne of <hi>Nuſe,</hi> and the xxvj. of the ſame, hee tooke it by aſſault.</p>
            <p>The tenth of December, at <hi>Limer</hi> a village lying by <hi>Tienen</hi> there rained blood vpon the Iſe, in a gentlemans Orchard, and it fell ſo hot, that there with the Iſe hiſſed, as if one had thruſt a pipe of Lead into it, &amp; ſunke at the leaſt a foot deepe into the Iſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:29"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1587</label> This yere vpon the xvij. of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie, the Frenchmen traiterouſly yeelded vp the Caſtle of <hi>Woud</hi> by <hi>Bergen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame month the towne of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenter</hi> was betraied to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> by Sir <hi>Edward Stanley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth of Iuly the towne of <hi>Gelder</hi> was betraied by a Scot cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Patron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt of Iulie, Rye was ſolde in <hi>Andwarpe</hi> for twelne Guilders, &amp; wheat for fifteene guilders the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>The ninth of Auguſt the towne of <hi>Sluce</hi> yeelded to the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> after he had ſhot <hi>16000</hi> Cannon ſhot at the towne.</p>
            <p>The ſame yere died <hi>Auguſtus Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue</hi> of <hi>Saxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1588</label> This yere the Queene of Scots was beheaded in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:30"/>
            <p>Not long before that, the Earle of <hi>Leceſter</hi> returned againe into the low Countries.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare hapned the trouble before <hi>Medenblicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame time the Lord of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt</hi> came into the Low Countries in the Queene of <hi>Englands</hi> behalfe.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare in Iune the Earle of <hi>Hollocke</hi> tooke the houſe of <hi>Loon,</hi> &amp; the Sconce of <hi>Enghelen</hi> in the water that goeth to <hi>Boſch,</hi> where <hi>Houtepen</hi> was ſlaine, and died at <hi>Hertogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bushe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixt of Iuly there was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion in <hi>Vtrecht</hi> betweene the Earle of <hi>Newenare,</hi> and the Magiſtrates &amp; Burgers.</p>
            <p>About Auguſt &amp; September, there was much talking of peace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the Queene of <hi>England</hi> ſent her Ambaſſadors out of <hi>England</hi> into
<pb facs="tcp:20663:30"/>
               <hi>Flanders,</hi> at the requeſt of the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> but it was all but treaſon.</p>
            <p>The twenty ſix of October, at <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> were executed <hi>Iaques Valmar. Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de Peſcarenges,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nicholas Mauld,</hi> and ſome for the ſame cauſe baniſhed out of the towne.</p>
            <p>The twentie three of December, <hi>Shenk</hi> tooke <hi>Bon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time the Prince of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> prepared diuers ſhips and flatte bottomed boates, at <hi>Andwarpe,</hi> and at <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> which did little profit or aide to the Spaniſh Fleet.</p>
            <p>The xxvij. of Februarie, <hi>1588.</hi> a woman in <hi>Dort</hi> was deliuered of iiij. men children at a birth, that were all liuing and chriſtned, their names be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob</hi> and <hi>Samuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth of March, <hi>Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge</hi> fell in a muteny.</p>
            <p>The xij. of Aprill, the Earle of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:31"/>was diſcharged of his gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by open placart. About this time died the king of <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie eight of Aprill, a woman in <hi>Dort</hi> was deliuered of three children at one birth, and chriſtned, <hi>Abraham, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> and <hi>Suſanna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the middle of May, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> thought to haue put out of <hi>Dunkerke</hi> with a great Fleet of Ships, but the <hi>Hollanders</hi> kept him in.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time the Queene of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> prepared her Nauy in a readines, &amp; made great preparation for the wars, although in the meane time a peace was intreated of.</p>
            <p>The thirteenth of May, a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Spaniſh ſhips ſet out of <hi>Lisbon</hi> for <hi>Gronie,</hi> whereof the like had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bin heard of, which was the Fleete that meant to haue done great hurt to <hi>England</hi> and the Low Countries, but
<pb facs="tcp:20663:31"/>God mercifully deliuered vs out of their hands.</p>
            <p>In Iuly the muteny at <hi>Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge</hi> was appeaſed.</p>
            <p>The xiiij. of September the Earle of <hi>Lec eſter</hi> died in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame moneth Sir <hi>Thomas Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> an Engliſh Gentleman came out of <hi>Indie</hi> with a ſhip laden with gold and ſiluer, hauing ſayled round about the world.</p>
            <p>The vij. of October, there was great mutenie in <hi>Vtrecht,</hi> where Captaine <hi>Clarehagen</hi> was ſtabbed, but died not of that wound.</p>
            <p>About this time the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> beſieged <hi>Bergen vp Zome,</hi> and went from it againe, not without both loſſe and ſhame.</p>
            <p>About this time Sir <hi>Martin Shenk</hi> made a Sconce aboue the towne <hi>Bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell</hi> vpon <hi>Voorne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:32"/>
            <p>The xix. of Nouember, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> departed from <hi>Bergen</hi> vpon <hi>Zone,</hi> after hee had beſieged it for the ſpace of ſixe weekes.</p>
            <p>The xxv. of September, <hi>Bon</hi> was deliuered vp to the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In October the Earle of <hi>Mansfelt</hi> beſieged <hi>Watchtendour,</hi> and the xx. of December, hee agreed with the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that they ſhould iſſue out all armed, with Enſignes diſplayed.</p>
            <p>The thirteenth of December, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> was ſlain by the king of <hi>France,</hi> which the <hi>Guiſart</hi> meant to haue done to him, and the next daie the Cardinall of <hi>Guiſe</hi> his Brother was likewiſe ſlaine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1589</label> This yeare <hi>Gertrudenberge</hi> was beſieged by the States, &amp; long bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, but in the end they left it off, &amp; the Souldiers within it ſolde the towne for fifteene moneths pay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:20663:32"/>the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> which they deliuered vpon the tenth of Aprill.</p>
            <p>The thirteenth of Aprill the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> tooke the houſe of <hi>Lobben,</hi> but within three dayes after hee loſt it againe.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenteene of May, the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard tooke the ſconce of <hi>Deeueren</hi> by <hi>Heuſden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twentie two of May, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> tooke the houſe of <hi>Hemart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twenty fiue of Iune he tooke the houſe of <hi>Blienbeeke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixteene of Iuly he tooke the houſes of <hi>Proyen</hi> &amp; <hi>Brakel,</hi> but now are left againe, and cleane burnt with the Dorpe.</p>
            <p>The fifteene of Iuly the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> beſieged <hi>Heuſden,</hi> and from thence hee went with ſhame enough into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:33"/>
            <p>The firſt of Auguſt, <hi>Henry</hi> the third King of <hi>France</hi> was murthered by a Frier.</p>
            <p>The eleauenth of Auguſt, Sir <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Shenke</hi> was drowned by <hi>Nimme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> thinking to haue taken the towne.</p>
            <p>The twentie foure of Auguſt, the enemie tooke the houſe of <hi>Heel</hi> in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melſweert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1590</label> This yeare vppon the fourth of March, Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> tooke the towne of <hi>Breda,</hi> by meanes of a ſhip of turfes wherin were about <hi>70.</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their leader beeing Captaine <hi>Argier</hi> of <hi>Lambrecht.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The xxvij. of September <hi>Hemert</hi> was yeelded to Graue <hi>Maurice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third of October hee likewiſe tooke the houſe of <hi>Heel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The xxix, of October <hi>Steenberghen</hi> was yeelded to the States.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20663:33"/>
            <p>The ſame yeare in the moneth of March, Graue <hi>Charles</hi> came before the Sconce of <hi>Seuenbergen</hi> with a great force thinking to take it, but with ſhame and loſſe of almoſt <hi>1000</hi> men, he was conſtrained to leaue it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1591</label> In <hi>Paris</hi> victuals were ſo deare, that it was compared to the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> for a towneſman therein conſtrained by hunger, hung his wife and children, which done he ſet a bill vpon his own breaſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he wrote the cauſe of that action, &amp; then hanged himſelfe, for at that time within the towne they eate Horſes, Aſſes, Dogges, Cats, Rats, &amp; Vine leaues, a pound of butter was ſolde for two Crownes, and an Egge for twelue ſolx, and great numbers died for hunger.</p>
            <p>The ſame yeare vppon the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſixe of May, <hi>Sutphen</hi> was beſieged
<pb facs="tcp:20663:34"/>and deliuered into the handes of Graue <hi>Maurice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thirty one of May, <hi>Deuenter</hi> was beſieged, and after it had receaued <hi>3700</hi> ſhotte againſt it, they yeelded it vnto the States.</p>
            <p>The twentie eight of Iune, Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> went before <hi>Delffile</hi> with three and thirtie great peeces, and the ſecond of Iuly it was yeelded vnto him.</p>
            <p>The fift of Iuly, hee came before the Sconce of <hi>Opſlach,</hi> and with <hi>160.</hi> ſhot battered it, which was yeelded to the States.</p>
            <p>Vpon the ſeauenth of Iuly the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers therein iſſuing diſarmed.</p>
            <p>The next day Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> went to the Sconce of <hi>Immentil,</hi> and after <hi>36.</hi> ſhot at the ſame, they yeelded it vnto him vpon the eleauenth of Iuly.</p>
            <p>The twenty foure of the ſame month fiue Cornets of horſe of the Prince of
<pb facs="tcp:20663:34"/>
               <hi>Parmas</hi> troupes were ouerthrowne in <hi>Betue,</hi> wherof one was the Prince of <hi>Parmas</hi> Guard.</p>
            <p>The twenty ſixe and twenty ſeuen of Iuly, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> left the Sconce of <hi>Knodſeburg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The xix. of September Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> deſieged <hi>Hulſt,</hi> which the xxv. of the ſame month yeelded vnto him.</p>
            <p>The xiiij. of October <hi>Kimmeghen</hi> was belieged, and th xxii. of the ſame month yeelded to Graue <hi>Maurice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This yere <hi>Steenwicke</hi> yeelded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Graue <hi>Maurice,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1592</label> vppon the fift of Iuly.</p>
            <p>The xxjj. of September, <hi>Couerden</hi> yeelded to the States.</p>
            <p>This yeare vppon the xxviij. of March, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1593</label> Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> with a great power went to beſiege <hi>Gertruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge,</hi> and the vij. of Aprill the enemy yelded vp the <hi>Steelhofes</hi> Sconce, by
<pb facs="tcp:20663:35"/>compoſition.</p>
            <p>The xxiiij. of Iune, the Bulwarke was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by force by Captaine <hi>Haen</hi> and <hi>Buury,</hi> whereby the towne was forced to yeelde to Graue <hi>Maurice,</hi> who let the ſouldiers iſſue out with their armes, but no colours.</p>
            <p>The xiiij. and xxj. of May, Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>120.</hi> companies of foote, &amp; xxvj. Cornets of horſemen departed from <hi>Swool</hi> to releeue <hi>Couerden,</hi> which had bin beſieged for the ſpace of ſixe months together, by the Earle <hi>Harman</hi> and <hi>Verdugo,</hi> but hearing of the ſtates forces, they left their forts, and departed, and ſo the towne was deliuered.</p>
            <p>The xxij. of Iuly, Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> tooke the towne of <hi>Gronning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This yeare vppon the xxviij. of March, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1595</label> about nine of the clocke a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> night the diche by <hi>Gorcum</hi> by a high
<pb facs="tcp:20663:35"/>water brake through, and ranne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Papendrecht.</p>
            <p>The xxiij. of Iuly, they began to digge without the ſpuyport of <hi>Dort,</hi> to enlarge the towne.</p>
            <p>The eleauenth of Auguſt foure &amp; fortie Dunkerkers and Spaniards, were hanged by <hi>Roterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>2</hi> of September, Earle <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> paſſed at <hi>Ramsburg</hi> ouer the <hi>Lip</hi> with fiue hundred men, where with other Earles hee fought moſt valiantly with <hi>Monſieur Dragons</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, in which ſight, the ſaid Earle <hi>Phillip,</hi> and the yong Earle of <hi>Solmes</hi> were ſlaine, yet <hi>Dragon</hi> loſt thrice as many men as Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> did.</p>
            <p>This yeare the ſeauenteene of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill <hi>Albertus</hi> Cardinall of <hi>Auſtria</hi> wan <hi>Callis</hi> from the French King. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1596</label>
            </p>
            <p>The thirtie of Iulie, the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with certaine <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:36"/>ſhips by force took the town of <hi>Cadyz Malis</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> which they ſpoiled, pilled, and burnt, bringing great treaſure from thence.</p>
            <p>The ſixteene of Iuly, there was a Comet or blazing ſtarre ſeene in the Low Countries.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenteene of Auguſt the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal tooke <hi>Hulſt</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition after he had loſt <hi>6000.</hi> of his beſt ſouldiers before the towne.</p>
            <p>This yeare vppon the twentie foure of Ianuarie, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1597</label> Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſixe thouſand men, met the enemy at <hi>Tuelſheheyde</hi> by <hi>Turenhoult,</hi> where he ſet vppon them, being a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who beeing aduertiſed of his comming fled away, whome he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and hauing ouertaken them, he ſlew of them to the number of two thouſand men, among the which, their Generall the Earle of <hi>Ferrara</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20663:36"/>was one.</p>
            <p>The eleauenth of March the towne of <hi>Amyens</hi> in <hi>France</hi> was by treaſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to the Cardinall for the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The nineteene of Auguſt the towne of <hi>Renisberg</hi> by compoſition was yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the States.</p>
            <p>The twentie foure of Auguſt the <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mille</hi> Sconce yeelded to Graue <hi>Maurice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond of September the towne of <hi>Meurs</hi> yeelded by compoſition vnto Graue <hi>Maurice.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
